Charles, you have finally
lost your senses.
This venture is impossible.
For some. Gentlemen, the only
way to achieve the impossible
is to believe it is possible.
That kind of thinking
could ruin you.
I'm willing to take that chance.
Imagine trading posts in
Rangoon, Bangkok, Jakarta...
The nightmare again?
I won't be long.
I'm falling down a dark hole,
then I see strange creatures.
What kind of creatures?
Well, there's a dodo bird, a rabbit
in a waistcoat, a smiling cat.
I didn't know cats could smile.
Neither did I.
And there's a blue caterpillar.
Blue caterpillar.
Hmm.
Do you think I've
gone round the bend?
I'm afraid so. You're mad,
bonkers, off your head.
But I'll tell you a secret.
All the best people are.
It's only a dream, Alice.
Nothing can harm you there.
But if you get too frightened, you
can always wake up. Like this.
Ow!
Must we go?
Doubt they'll notice
if we never arrive.
They will notice.
Where's your corset?
And no stockings.
I'm against them.
But you're not properly dressed.
Who's to say what is proper?
What if it was agreed that "proper"
was wearing a codfish on your head?
- Would you wear it?
- Alice.
To me, a corset is
like a codfish.
Please, not today.
Father would have laughed.
I'm sorry. I'm tired. I
didn't sleep well last night.
Did you have bad dreams again?
Only one.
It's always the same, ever
since I can remember.
Do you think that's normal?
Don't most people have
different dreams?
I don't know.
There. You're beautiful.
Now, can you manage a smile?
At last. We thought
you'd never arrive.
Alice, Hamish is waiting
to dance with you. Go.
You do realize it's
well past 4:00.
Now everything will have
to be rushed through.
- I am sorry.
- Oh, never mind!
Forgive my wife. She's been planning
this affair for over 20 years.
If only Charles were here...
My condolences.
I think of your husband often.
He was truly a man of vision.
I hope you don't think I've taken
advantage of your misfortunes.
Of course not. I'm pleased that
you purchased the company.
I was a fool for not investing in his
mad venture when I had the chance.
Charles thought so, too.
Hamish, do you ever
tire of quadrille?
On the contrary. I
find it invigorating.
Do I amuse you?
No.
I had a sudden vision of
all the ladies in trousers
and the men wearing dresses.
I think you'll do best to keep
your visions to yourself.
When in doubt, remain silent.
Pardon us, sir. Miss Kingsleigh
is distracted today.
Where's your head?
I was wondering what it
would be like to fly.
Why would you spend your time
thinking about such
an impossible thing?
Why wouldn't I?
My father said he sometimes
believed in 6 impossible things
before breakfast.
Come along.
Alice, meet me under the gazebo
in precisely 10 minutes.
We have a secret to tell you.
If you're telling me, then
it's not much of a secret.
- Perhaps we shouldn't.
- We decided we should.
If we tell her, she
won't be surprised.
- Will you be surprised?
- Not if you tell me.
But now you've brought
it up, you have to.
- No, we don't.
- In fact, we won't.
I wonder if your mother knows
that you two swim naked
in the Havershims' pond.
- You wouldn't.
- Oh, but I would.
There's your mother right now.
Hamish is going to
ask for your hand.
You've ruined the surprise!
I could strangle them!
Everyone went to so much
effort to keep the secret.
Does everyone know?
It's why they've all come.
This is your engagement party.
Hamish will ask you under the
gazebo. When you say yes...
But I don't know if I
want to marry Hamish.
Who, then? You won't
do better than a lord.
You'll soon be 20, Alice. That
pretty face won't last forever.
You don't want to end
up like Aunt Imogene.
And you don't want to be a
burden on Mother, do you?
No.
So you'll marry Hamish.
You will be as happy
as I am with Lowell,
and your life will be perfect.
It's already decided.
Alice, dear.
I'll leave you to it.
Shall we take a leisurely stroll
through the garden, just you and me?
Do you know what
I've always dreaded?
The decline of the aristocracy?
Ugly grandchildren.
But you're lovely.
You're bound to produce
little... Imbeciles!
The gardeners have
planted white roses
when I specifically
asked for red.
You could always
paint the roses red.
What an odd thing to say.
You should know that my son has
extremely delicate digestion.
- Did you see that?
- See what?
- It was a rabbit, I think.
- Nasty things.
I do enjoy setting
the dogs on them.
If you serve Hamish the wrong
foods, he could get a blockage.
Did you see it that time?
- See what?
- The rabbit.
Don't shout.
Now, pay attention. Hamish said
you were easily distracted.
- What was I saying?
- Hamish has a blockage.
I couldn't be more interested,
but you'll have to excuse me.
Aunt Imogene.
I think I'm going mad. I keep
seeing a rabbit in a waistcoat.
I can't be bothered with
your fancy rabbit now.
I'm waiting for my fiance.
- You have a fiance?
- Hmm.
There! Did you see it?
He's a prince.
But, alas, he cannot marry me
unless he renounces his throne.
It's tragic, isn't it?
Very.
Lowell?
Alice. We were just...
Hattie's an old friend.
I can see you're very close.
Look, you won't mention this
to your sister, will you?
I don't know. I'm confused.
I need time to think.
Well, think about Margaret.
She'd never trust me again.
You don't want to ruin
her marriage, do you?
Me?
But I'm not the one who's
sneaking around behind her back.
There you are.
Alice Kingsleigh...
Hamish.
What is it?
You have a caterpillar
on your shoulder.
Ew.
Don't hurt it.
You'll want to wash that finger.
Alice Kingsleigh,
will you be my wife?
Well,
everyone expects me to,
and you're a lord.
My face won't last, and I
don't want to end up like...
But this is happening
so quickly. I...
I think I...
I need a moment.
Hello.
It's only a dream.
You'd think she would remember
all this from the first time.
You've brought
the wrong Alice.
No, she's the right one.
I'm certain of it.
She's the wrong Alice.
Give her a chance.
Curiouser and curiouser.
I told you she's
the right Alice.
I am not convinced.
How is that for gratitude?
I've been up there for weeks,
trailing one Alice after the next,
and I was almost eaten
by other animals.
Can you imagine?
They go about entirely unclothed,
and they do their shukm in public.
- I had to avert my eyes.
- Doesn't look anything like herself.
That's because she's
the wrong Alice.
- If she was, she might be.
- If she isn't, she ain't.
- But if she were so, she would be.
- But she isn't, nohow.
How can I be the wrong Alice
when this is my dream?
And who are you, if I might ask?
Oh, I'm Tweedledee,
he's Tweedledum.
Contrariwise, I'm Tweedledum,
he's Tweedledee.
We should consult Absolem.
Exactly. Absolem will
know who she is.
- I'll escort you.
- Hey, it's not being your turn.
So unfair.
- Hey, leave off!
- Let go!
- Are they always this way?
- Family trait.
You can both escort her.
- Who is this Absolem?
- He's wise. He's absolute.
He's Absolem.
Who are you?
Absolem?
You're not Absolem, I'm Absolem.
The question is, who are you?
Alice.
We shall see.
What do you mean by that?
I ought to know who I am.
Yes, you ought, stupid girl.
Unroll the Oraculum.
The Oraculum, being a calendrical
compendium of Underland.
- It's a calendar.
- Compendium.
It tells of each and every
day since the Beginning.
Today is Griblig Day in the
time of the Red Queen.
Show her the Frabjous Day.
Mmm. Yeah, Frabjous being the
day you slay the Jabberwocky.
Sorry? Slay a what?
Oh, yeah. That being you,
there, with the Vorpal sword.
No other swords can kill
the Jabberwocky, nohow.
If it ain't Vorpal,
it ain't dead.
That's not me!
I know!
Resolve this for us, Absolem.
Is she the right Alice?
Not hardly.
- I told you.
- Oh, dear.
- I said so.
Contrariwise, you
said she might be.
No, you said she
would be if she was.
Little impostor. Pretending to
be Alice. She should be ashamed.
I was so certain of you.
I'm sorry. I don't mean
to be the wrong Alice.
Wait, this is my dream.
I'm going to wake up now
and you'll all disappear.
That's odd. Pinching
usually does the trick.
I could stick you,
if that would help.
- It might, actually.
- Thank you. My pleasure.
Ow!
- Bandersnatch!
Wait.
It's only a dream.
Nothing can hurt me.
What's she doing?
Can't hurt me. Can't hurt me.
Run, you great lug!
This way, east to Queast.
No, South to Snud.
No. No, no. This way.
Someone has stolen
three of my tarts!
- Did you steal them?
- No, Your Majesty.
- Did you?
- Did you steal them?
- No, Your Majesty.
Did you steal my tarts?
No, Your Majesty.
Squimberry juice.
- I was so hungry! I didn't mean to!
- Off with his head!
My family! Oh, please,
please don't!
No! I have little
ones to look after!
Go to his house and
collect the little ones.
I love tadpoles on toast almost
as much as I love caviar.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Drink!
Majesty?
Ilosovic Stayne, you knave,
where have you been lurking?
Majesty, I have
found the Oraculum.
That? Looks so ordinary
for an oracle.
Look here, on the Frabjous Day.
I'd know that tangled
mess of hair anywhere.
Is it Alice?
I believe it is.
What's she doing with
my darling Jabberwocky?
She appears to be slaying it.
She killed my Jabber-baby-wocky?
Not yet, but it will happen
if we don't stop her.
Find Alice, Stayne. Find her!
Find the scent of human
girl and earn your freedom.
For my wife and pups, as well?
Everyone will go home.
Dogs will believe anything.
It looks like you ran afoul of
something with wicked claws.
And I'm still dreaming.
What did that to you?
- Banner or Bander...
- The Bandersnatch?
Well, I'd better have a look.
What are you doing?
It needs to be purified by
someone with evaporating skills,
or it will fester and putrefy.
I'd rather you didn't. I'll
be fine as soon as I wake up.
At least let me bind it for you.
- What do you call yourself?
- Alice.
The Alice?
- There's been some debate about that.
- I never get involved in politics.
You'd best be on your way.
What way? All I want to do
is wake up from this dream.
Fine.
Then I'll take you to the Hare and the
Hatter, but that's the end of it.
Coming?
Watch what you're doing!
Hey, watch it!
Okay, okay. All right.
It's you.
No, it's not. McTwisp
brought us the wrong Alice.
It's the wrong Alice!
It's absolutely Alice.
You're absolutely Alice.
I'd know you anywhere.
I'd know him anywhere.
Well, as you can see,
we're still having tea.
And it's all because I was obliged to
kill Time waiting for your return.
You're terribly late, you know.
Naughty.
Well, anyway, Time became quite
offended and stopped altogether.
Not a tick ever since.
- Cup.
- Time can be funny in dreams.
Yes, yes, of course, but
now you're back, you see,
and we need to get on
to the Frabjous Day.
- Frabjous Day!
I'm investigating things that
begin with the letter "M."
Have you any idea why a raven
is like a writing desk?
- Downal wyth Bluddy Behg Hid!
- What?
- Down with the Bloody Big Head,
the Bloody Big Head
being the Red Queen.
Come, come. We simply must commence
with the slaying and such.
Therefore, it is high time
to forgive and forget
or forget and forgive,
whichever comes first
or is, in any case, most
convenient. I'm waiting.
Hey. It's tick-tick...
It's ticking again.
All this talk of blood and
slaying has put me off my tea.
Ah.
The entire world is falling to ruin
and poor Chessur's off his tea.
What happened that day
was not my fault.
Oh, dear.
You ran out on them to
save your own skin,
you guddler's scuttish pilgar lickering
shukm juggling sluking urpal.
Bar lom muck egg brimni!
Hatter!
- Thank you.
- Meow.
I'm fine.
What's wrong with you, Tarrant? You
used to be the life of the party.
You used to do the best
Futterwacken in all of Witzend.
- Futter what?
- Futterwacken!
It's a dance.
On the Frabjous Day,
when the White Queen once
again wears the crown,
on that day, I shall
Futterwacken vigorously.
Oh, no.
Uh-oh.
The Knave.
Goodbye.
Hide her!
Drink this quickly.
Quick! Hide her!
Oh, dear.
Aye.
Mind your head.
Let me out!
Well, if it's not my
favorite trio of lunatics.
Would you like to join us?
You're all late for tea!
We're looking for the
girl called Alice.
Speaking of the Queen, here is a little
song we used to sing in her honor.
- Twinkle Twinkle little bat.
- How I wonder where you're at.
- Up a...
If you're hiding her,
you'll lose your heads.
Already lost them.
All together now!
- Up above the world you fly.
- Like a tea tray in the sky.
- Twinkle, twinkle, twinkle, twinkle.
- Twinkle, twinkle, twinkle.
- Twinkle, twinkle, twinkle...
Oh!
Downal wyth Bluddy Behg Hid!
Would you like some cream?
- Would you like a slice of Battenberg?
- Follow the bloodhound.
- Sugar?
- Yes, please.
- Oh, that's lovely.
- You're all mad.
Thanks very much.
Pass the scones, please.
- That one there.
- Oh! Pardon.
Yes. Yep, aye.
One moment.
There. Yes.
Try this on for size.
Oh.
I like it.
Good thing the bloodhound is
one of us, or you'd be...
What do they want with me?
Wait a minute, best take
her to the White Queen.
She'll be safe there. Spoon...
Your carriage, milady.
- The hat?
- Of course.
Anyone can go by horse or rail,
but the absolute best way to travel
is by hat. Have I made a rhyme?
Oh, I love traveling by hat.
Mally. Just Alice, please.
Fairfarren, all.
What do you mean? Wait. Gae!
"'Twas brillig, and the slithy toves
Did gyre and gimble in the wabe."
"All mimsy were the borogoves
And the mome raths outgrabe."
Sorry, what was that?
What was what?
"The Jabberwock, with eyes of flame
Jaws that bite and claws that catch!"
"Beware the Jabberwock, my son!
And the frumious Bandersnatch!."
"He took his Vorpal sword in hand The
Vorpal blade went snicker-snack!"
"He left it dead, and with its
head He went galumphing back."
It's all about you, you know.
I'm not slaying anything. I don't
slay, so put it out of your mind.
Mind.
Wait! You can't leave me here!
You don't slay.
Do you have any idea what
the Red Queen has done?
You don't slay.
I couldn't if I wanted to.
You're not the same
as you were before.
You were much more muchier.
You've lost your muchness.
My "muchness"?
In there. Something's missing.
Tell me what Red Queen has done.
It's not a pretty story.
Tell me anyway.
It was here.
I was hatter to the White
Queen at the time.
Hightopp clan have always
been employed at court.
Hatter? Hatter!
I'm fine.
Are you?
Did you hear that? I'm
certain I heard something.
What?
Oh! Red Knights.
Go South to Trotter's Bottom.
The White Queen's
castle is just beyond.
Hold on tightly.
Down with the bloody Red Queen!
You were supposed to lead them
away! The Hatter trusted you!
They have my wife and pups.
- What's your name?
- Bayard.
Sit!
Would your name be
Alice, by any chance?
Yes, but I'm not the one that
everyone's talking about.
The Hatter would not have given
himself up just for any Alice.
Where did they take him?
To the Red Queen's
castle at Salazen Grum.
We're going to rescue him.
That is not foretold.
I don't care. He wouldn't be
there if it weren't for me.
The Frabjous Day
is almost upon us.
You must prepare to
meet the Jabberwocky.
From the moment I fell
down that rabbit hole,
I've been told what I must
do and who I must be.
I've been shrunk, stretched,
scratched and stuffed into a teapot.
I've been accused of being Alice and of
not being Alice, but this is my dream.
I'll decide where
it goes from here.
If you diverge from the path...
I make the path.
Take me to Salazen Grum, Bayard,
and don't forget the hat.
There's only one way across.
Lost my muchness, have I?
Bayard! The hat!
Your Majesty.
So sorry.
Splendid shot!
Where's my ball? Page!
Yes, Your Majesty.
I want to help you.
Well, if it isn't
the wrong Alice.
What brings you here? Mmm?
I've come to rescue the Hatter.
You're not rescuing anyone
being the size of a gerbil.
Well, do you have any more of that
cake that made me grow before?
Upelkuchen? Actually, I
might have some left.
Not all of it!
Oh, no! Stop! No, no, no, don't.
Don't do that!
Page!
Oh, dear.
And what is this?
It... It's a "who," Majesty.
This is, um...
Um?
From Umbradge.
What happened to your clothes?
I outgrew them. I've been
growing an awful lot lately.
I tower over everyone in
Umbradge. They laugh at me.
So I've come to you, hoping you
might understand what it's like.
My dear girl,
anyone with a head that large
is welcome in my court.
Someone find her some clothes!
Use the curtains if you must,
but clothe this enormous girl.
I need a pig here!
I love a warm pig belly
for my aching feet.
- Would you like one, Um?
- No, thank you.
Sit!
Go away.
Where are my fat boys?
You must meet them.
Fat boys!
Oh. There they are.
Aren't they adorable?
They have the oddest way of
speaking. Speak, boys. Amuse us.
Go on.
No.
Speak!
- Is that being...
- No, no, it isn't. Not a bit. No.
Contrariwise, I believe it's so.
No, it ain't so, nohow!
I love my fat boys.
Now, get out.
- He did pinch me.
And who is this lovely creature?
Um, my new favorite.
- Well, does she have a name?
- Um.
I believe your name has
slipped the Queen's mind.
Her name is Um, idiot!
From Umbradge.
Any luck with the prisoner?
He's stubborn.
You're too soft. Bring him!
We know Alice has
returned to Underland.
Do you know where she is?
I've been considering things
that begin with the letter "M."
Moron, mutiny, murder, malice.
We're looking for an "A"
word now. Where is Alice?
Who, that wee little boy?
I wouldn't know.
What if I take off your head?
Will you know then?
Stop that.
What a regrettably
large head you have.
I should very much
like to hat it.
- Hat it?
- Yes.
I used to hat the White
Queen, you know.
Wasn't very much to
work with, poor dear.
Her head is so small.
It's tiny. It's a
pimple of a head.
But this...
What I could do with this
monument, this orb...
Nay, this magnificently
heroic globe.
What could you do?
Unbind him, Stayne.
How can he work if
his hands are bound?
Well, then, shall it be
a bonnet or a boater?
Or something for the boudoir?
Cloche, dunce hat, death cap, coif,
snood, barboosh, pugree, yarmulke,
cockle hat, porkpie, tam o'shanter,
billycock, bicorne, tricorne, bandeau,
bongrace, fan-tail, night
cap, Garibaldi, fez...
Hatter.
Fez?
Leave us.
The trees seem sad.
- Have you been speaking with them?
- Yes, Your Majesty.
Perhaps a bit more kindly.
Would you all excuse me
for a moment? Thank you.
- What news, Bayard?
- Alice has returned to Underland.
- Where is she now?
- In Salazen Grum.
Forgive me. I allowed her to
divert from her destined path.
No, no, no, no. But that is exactly
where she will find the Vorpal sword.
We have our champion. Rest now.
You've done well.
Have you seen a
hat around here?
You must find Alice, Stayne.
Without the Jabberwocky,
my sister's followers will
surely rise against me.
Ugly little sister. Why do
they adore her and not me?
I cannot fathom it. You are
far superior in all ways.
I know.
But Mirana can make anyone
fall in love with her.
Men, women,
Even the furniture.
Even the King?
I had to do it. He
would have left me.
Majesty, is it not better
to be feared than loved?
Not certain anymore.
Oh, let her have the rabble.
I don't need them.
I have you.
They're wonderful.
You must let me try one on.
It is good to be working
at my trade again.
It's just a pity you have
to make them for her.
What is the hatter with me?
Hatter?
Hatter.
Have you any idea why a raven
is like a writing desk?
I'm frightened, Alice.
I don't like it in here.
It's terribly crowded.
Have I gone mad?
I'm afraid so. You're
entirely bonkers.
But I'll tell you a secret.
All the best people are.
Here.
That's better. You
look yourself again.
Hat man! Where are my hats?
I'm not a patient monarch!
I'm told she keeps the Vorpal
sword hidden in the castle.
The rabbit will help you.
Find it, Alice. Take
it to the White Queen.
We'll go to the White
Queen together.
Why is it you're always
too small or too tall?
- Tweedles.
- Alice.
- How do you do, again?
- Where's the rabbit?
How is it you're
being so great big?
She ain't great big, this
is how she normal is.
I'm certain she's
smaller when we met.
No, she drank the pishsalver to
get through the door, recall it?
Oh, yeah.
- Where's the rabbit?
- Over theres.
- What are you doing here?
- I'm rescuing the Hatter.
I'm rescuing the Hatter.
He told me that the Vorpal sword is
hidden in the castle. Help me find it.
I don't take orders from
big, clumsy, galumphing...
Shoo!
- What is it, McTwisp?
- I know where the sword is.
The sword's hidden inside.
Be careful, Alice.
I know that smell.
I'm not going in there.
Look what that thing
did to my arm.
Dear, oh, dear. Why haven't
you mentioned this?
It wasn't this bad before.
Hatter? Where are you?
Hatter?
Mallymkun.
Do you still have the
Bandersnatch eye?
Right here.
- I need it.
- Come and get it.
Hey! Give it back!
I like you, Um.
I like largeness.
Get away from me.
I have your eye.
No.
Hmm.
You look stunning in that hat.
Yes. Next.
Your Majesty has
never looked better.
Hmm. Another.
Oh!
I don't wish to alarm you,
but it smells as though you
might have dropped something.
Never mind him, he's mad.
Come along.
Stayne!
I suppose this
makes us even now.
Um forced herself on me.
I told her my heart belongs to
you, but she's obsessed with me.
Off with her head!
Stand back, Mallymkun.
How's this for muchness?
No, no! It mustn't be
used for anything...
Arrest that girl for
unlawful seduction!
Hatter!
- Take it to the White Queen.
- I'm not leaving without you.
Go!
Run, Alice!
Alice?
Run!
Seize her.
Alice.
Of course. Why didn't I see it?
Well, it has been a long time, and
you were such a little tyke then.
- Give me the sword.
- Stay back.
The Queen will be so pleased.
She will take great pleasure
in taking off your head.
- Oh, Alice! Bayard!
- To Marmoreal.
Majesty, Alice has escaped
on the Bandersnatch,
with the Vorpal sword.
How could you let this happen?
I may have underestimated her,
but we have her conspirators,
the Hatter and a dormouse.
Off with their heads!
Welcome to Marmoreal.
I believe this belongs to you.
Mmm.
The Vorpal sword is home again.
The armor is complete.
Now all we need is a champion.
You're a little taller
than I thought you'd be.
Blame it on too much upelkuchen.
Oh.
Come with me.
Is the March Hare here?
You're late for your
soup, you wee besom.
- You're late for your soup.
- Could use some salt.
Come here, you!
Give me that here. Choppy,
chop, chop, chop.
Leek and potato. Yes.
That would be...
Pishsalver. Let me think.
A pinch of worm fat,
urine of the horsefly,
buttered fingers.
My sister preferred to study
Dominion Over Living Things.
Tell me, how does
she seem to you?
Perfectly horrid.
- And her head?
- Bulbous.
I think she may have some
kind of growth in there,
something pressing on her brain.
Three coins from a dead man's pocket,
two teaspoons of wishful thinking.
You can't imagine the things
that go on in that place.
Oh, yes, I can.
But when a champion steps forth
to slay the Jabberwocky,
the people will
rise against her.
That should do it.
Blow.
- Feel better?
- Much, thank you.
There's someone here who would
like to speak with you.
- Absolem?
- Who are you?
I thought we'd settled this.
I'm Alice, but not that one.
- How do you know?
- You said so yourself.
I said you were
not hardly Alice,
but you're much more her now.
In fact, you're almost Alice.
Even so,
I couldn't slay the Jabberwocky
if my life depended on it.
It will.
So I suggest you keep the
Vorpal sword on hand
when the Frabjous Day arrives.
You seem so real.
Sometimes I forget that
this is all a dream.
Will you stop doing that?
I've always admired that hat.
Hello, Chess.
Since you won't be
needing it anymore,
would you consider
bequeathing it to me?
How dare you?
It is a formal execution. I would
like to look my best, you know.
It is a pity about all this.
I was looking forward to
seeing you Futterwacken.
I was rather good
at it, was I not?
I really do love that hat.
I would wear it to all
the finest occasions.
I love a morning
execution, don't you?
- Yes, Your Majesty.
- I'd like to keep it on.
- Suit yourself.
As long as I can
get at your neck.
I'm right behind you.
Off with his head!
I can't watch.
Good morning, everyone.
Chess, you dog.
Madam,
you are being
heinously bamboozled
by these lickspittle toadies
you surround yourselves with.
What is that?
I'm not the only one, Majesty.
Look!
A counterfeit nose. You
should be ashamed.
Me? What about that big
belly you're so proud of?
Liars! Cheats! Falsifiers!
Off with their heads!
The abused and enslaved
in the Red Queen's court,
all of you stand up and fight!
Rise up against the
bloody Red Queen.
- Downal wyth Bluddy Behg Hid!
Release the Jubjub Bird!
You're right, Stayne,
it is far better to
be feared than loved.
Come, boys. Quickly! Come on!
Hatter!
Come on, Mally, quickly.
Come on. Come on.
Prepare the Jabberwocky for battle.
We're going to visit my little sister.
I had hoped to have
a champion by now.
Why don't you slay the
Jabberwocky yourself?
You must have the power.
It is against my vows to
harm any living creature.
We have company.
Have a look, Bayard.
Bielle.
I'm so happy to see you. I
thought they were going to...
So did I. But they didn't, and now
here I am, still in one piece.
And I'm rather glad about that
now that I'm seeing you again.
I would have regretted
not seeing you again,
especially now that you're
you, and the proper size.
And it's a good size. It's a great
size. It's a right proper Alice size!
- Hatter. Size.
- Fez. I'm fine.
Where's your hat?
Mmm.
- Cheshire.
- How's the arm, love?
All healed.
Goodbye, sweet hat.
Have you any idea why a raven
is like a writing desk?
Let me think about it.
You know what tomorrow
is, don't you?
Frabjous Day. How
could I forget?
Wish I'd wake up.
- Still believe this is a dream, do you?
- Of course.
This has all come
from my own mind.
Which would mean
that I'm not real.
Afraid so. You're just a
figment of my imagination.
I would dream up someone
who's half-mad.
Yes, yes. But you would have
to be half-mad to dream me up.
I must be, then.
I'll miss you when I wake up.
Who will step forth to be
champion for the White Queen?
That would be I.
You have very poor evaporating
skills. I should be the one.
I'll do it.
- No, me.
No other slayer, nohow.
If it ain't Alice,
it ain't dead.
Alice, you cannot live your
life to please others.
The choice must be yours,
because when you step out
to face that creature,
you will step out alone.
Nothing was ever
accomplished with tears.
Absolem?
Why are you upside down?
I've come to the
end of this life.
- You're going to die?
- Transform.
Don't go. I need your help.
I don't know what to do.
I can't help you if you don't even
know who you are, stupid girl.
I'm not stupid.
My name is Alice.
I live in London.
I have a mother named Helen
and a sister named Margaret.
My father was
Charles Kingsleigh.
He had a vision that stretched
halfway around the world,
and nothing ever stopped him.
I'm his daughter. I'm
Alice Kingsleigh.
Alice, at last.
You were just as dim-witted
the first time you were here.
You called it "Wonderland,"
as I recall.
Wonderland.
- What do you call yourself?
- Alice.
The Alice?
Then I'll take you to the Hare and the
Hatter, but that's the end of it.
She's the right one.
I'm certain of it.
Ah, Thackery, not at
the table, please.
Have some tea.
You're not Absolem, I'm
Absolem, stupid girl.
- What is this?
- I'm Tweedledee, he's Tweedledum.
Contrariwise, I'm Tweedledum,
he's Tweedledee.
You'd think she would remember
all this from the first time.
Curiouser and curiouser.
It wasn't a dream at
all, it was a memory.
This place is real, and so are
you and so is the Hatter.
And the Jabberwocky.
Remember, the Vorpal sword
knows what it wants.
All you have to do
is hold on to it.
Fairfarren, Alice. Perhaps I
will see you in another life.
- Hello, Iracebeth.
- Hello, Mirana.
On this, the Frabjous Day,
the Queens Red and White
shall send forth their champions
to do battle on their behalf.
Oh, Racie. We don't
have to fight.
I know what you're doing.
You think you can blink
those pretty little eyes
and I'll melt, just like
Mummy and Daddy did.
Please.
No! It is my crown!
I am the eldest!
Jabberwocky!
This is impossible.
Only if you believe it is.
Sometimes I believe as many as
6 impossible things before breakfast.
That is an excellent practice.
However, just at the moment,
you really might want to
focus on the Jabberwocky.
Where's your champion, Sister?
Here.
Hello, Um.
6 impossible things.
Count them, Alice.
1, there's a potion
that can make you shrink.
2, and a cake that
can make you grow.
So, my old foe, we meet on
the battlefield once again.
We've never met.
Not you, insignificant bearer.
My ancient enemy,
the Vorpal one.
That's enough chatter.
3, animals can talk.
4, Alice,
cats can disappear.
5,
there's a place
called Wonderland.
6,
I can slay the Jabberwocky.
The Hatter's interfering!
Off with his head!
Off with your head!
Kill her!
We follow you no more,
Bloody Big Head.
How dare you? Off with his head!
Iracebeth of Crims, your crimes against
Underland are worthy of death.
However, that is
against my vows,
therefore, you are
banished to the Outlands.
No one is to show you any kindness,
or ever speak a word to you.
You will not have a
friend in the world.
Majesty, I hope you
bear me no ill will.
Only this one, Ilosovic Stayne,
you are to join
Iracebeth in banishment
from this day until
the end of Underland.
At least we have each other.
Majesty, please! Kill me!
Please!
But I do not owe you a kindness.
- Take off my head!
- He tried to kill me.
- Majesty! Please! Please!
- I offer you my head!
- He tried to kill me!
Oh, the Frabjous Day!
Callou! Callay!
- What is he doing?
- Futterwacken.
Blood of the Jabberwocky. You
have our everlasting gratitude.
And for your efforts
on our behalf...
- Will this take me home?
- If that is what you choose.
You could stay.
What an idea. A crazy,
mad, wonderful idea.
But I can't.
There are questions I have to
answer, things I have to do.
Be back again
before you know it.
You won't remember me.
Of course I will.
How could I forget?
Hatter, why is a raven
like a writing desk?
I haven't the slightest idea.
Fairfarren, Alice.
She left me standing
there without an answer.
A case of nerves, no doubt.
- Alice.
- Lord, Good Lord.
- Are you all right?
- What happened to you?
I fell down a hole
and hit my head.
I'm sorry, Hamish. I can't marry you.
You're not the right man for me.
And there's that trouble
with your digestion.
I love you, Margaret, but this is my
life. I'll decide what to do with it.
You're lucky to have my
sister for your wife, Lowell,
and you be good to her. I'll
be watching very closely.
There is no prince,
Aunt Imogene.
You need to talk to someone
about these delusions.
I happen to love rabbits,
especially white ones.
Don't worry, Mother,
I'll find something useful
to do with my life.
You two remind me of some
funny boys I met in a dream.
- You've left me out.
- No, I haven't, sir.
You and I have
business to discuss.
Shall we speak in the study?
Oh. And one more thing.
My father told me he planned to expand
his trade route to Sumatra and Borneo,
but I don't think he was
looking far enough.
Why not go all the way to China?
It's vast, the culture is rich, and
we have a foothold in Hong Kong.
To be the first to trade with
China, can you imagine it?
You know, if anybody else
had said that to me,
I'd say, "You've
lost your senses."
But I've seen that look before.
Well, as you're not going
to be my daughter-in-law,
perhaps you'd consider becoming
an apprentice with the company.
Hello, Absolem.
Tripping out, spinning around.
I'm underground I fell down.
Yeah, I fell down.
I'm freaking out
Where am I now?
Upside down and I
can't stop it now.
Can't stop me now.
I, I'll get by.
I, I'll survive.
When the world's crashing down
When I fall and hit the ground.
I will turn myself around
Don't you try to stop me.
I, I won't cry.
I found myself in Wonderland.
Get back on my
feet, the ground.
Is this real?
Is it pretend?
I'll take a stand
until the end.
I, I'll get by.
I, I'll survive.
When the world's crashing down
When I fall and hit the ground.
I will turn myself around
Don't you try to stop me.
I, I won't cry.
Oh, Alice, dear,
where have you been?
So near, so far,
so in between.
What have you heard?
What have you seen?
Alice, Alice, please, Alice.
Oh, tell us, are
you big or small?
To try this one
or try them all.
It's such a long,
long way to fall.
Alice, Alice, oh, Alice.
How can you know
this way, not that?
You choose the door
You choose the path.
Perhaps you should
be coming back.
Another day, another day.
And nothing is quite
what it seems.
You're dreaming
Are you dreaming?
Oh, Alice.
Oh!
Oh, how will you
find your way?
No time for tears today
No time for tears today.
So many doors, how
did you choose?
So much to gain,
so much to lose.
So many things
got in your way.
No time today, no time today.
Be careful not to
lose your head.
Remember what the
dormouse said.
Alice!
Did someone pull
you by the hand?
How many Miles to Wonderland?
Please tell us so
we'll understand.
Alice, Alice, oh, Alice.
Oh, how will you
find your way?