NARRATOR: With the coming
of the Second World War...
...many eyes in imprisoned Europe
turned hopefully, or desperately...
...toward the freedom of the Americas.
Lisbon became
the great embarkation point.
But not everybody could get
to Lisbon directly.
And so a torturous, roundabout
refugee trail sprang up.
Paris to Marseilles...
...across the Mediterranean to Oran.
Then, by train or auto or foot,
across the rim of Africa...
...to Casablanca in French Morocco.
Here, the fortunate ones,
through money or influence or luck...
...might obtain exit visas
and scurry to Lisbon.
And from Lisbon to the New World.
But the others wait in Casablanca.
And wait and wait...
...and wait.
[CHATTERING]
To all officers:
Two German couriers carrying official
documents murdered on train from Oran.
Murderer and possible accomplices
headed for Casablanca.
Round up all suspicious characters
and search them for stolen document.
Important.
[SPEAKS IN FRENCH]
[SIREN WAILING]
May we see your papers?
I don't think I have them on me.
- In that case, you'll have to come along.
- Wait. It's possible that I...
Yes. Here they are.
These papers expired three weeks ago.
You'll have to come along.
Halt!
[GUN FIRES]
- What on earth is going on there?
MAN: I don't know, my dear.
Pardon, monsieur. Pardon, madame.
Have you not heard?
We hear very little,
and we understand even less.
Two German couriers
were found murdered in the desert.
The unoccupied desert.
This is the customary roundup
of refugees, liberals...
...and, of course, a beautiful young girl
for Renault, the prefect of police.
Along with these unhappy refugees...
...the scum of Europe
has gravitated to Casablanca.
Some of them have been waiting
years for a visa.
I beg of you, monsieur, watch yourself.
Be on guard.
This place is full of vultures.
Vultures everywhere. Everywhere!
- Thank you. Thank you very much.
- Not at all. Au revoir, monsieur.
- Au revoir, madame.
- Au revoir.
What an amusing little fellow.
Waiter.
- Oh, how silly of me.
- What, dear?
I've left my wallet in the hotel.
[PLANE ENGINE ROARING]
Perhaps tomorrow
we'll be on the plane.
[SPEAKS IN GERMAN]
MAN: Heil Hitler.
CROWD: Heil Hitler.
It is good to see you again,
Major Strasser.
Thank you, thank you.
May I present Captain Renault, police
prefect of Casablanca. Major Strasser.
Unoccupied France welcomes you
to Casablanca.
Thank you, captain.
It's good to be here.
Major Strasser, my aide,
Lieutenant Casselle.
Captain Tonnelli.
The Italian service at your command.
That is kind of you.
[SPEAKING IN ITALIAN]
You may find the climate
of Casablanca a trifle warm.
We Germans must get used to all
climates, from Russia to the Sahara.
Perhaps you
weren't referring to weather.
What else?
The murder of the couriers.
What has been done?
My men are rounding up
twice the usual number of suspects.
But we know already
who the murderer is.
Good. Is he in custody?
No hurry. Tonight he'll be at Rick's.
Everybody comes to Rick's.
I've already heard about this café.
And also about Mr. Rick himself.
[BAND PLAYING]
[MAN SINGING "IT HAD TO BE YOU"]
It had to be you
I wandered around and finally found
The somebody who
Could make me be true
Could make me be blue
And even be glad just to be sad
Thinking of you
Some others I've seen
Might never be mean
Might never be cross, or try to be boss
But they wouldn't do
For nobody else gave me a thrill
Honey, with all your faults
I love you still
Had to be you, wonderful you
Had to be you
[SINGING "SHINE"]
'Cause my hair is curly
'Cause my teeth are pearly
Waiting, waiting, waiting.
I'll never get out of here.
I'll die in Casablanca.
But can't you make it
just a little more?
Please?
Sorry, but diamonds are a drug on
the market. Everybody sells diamonds.
There are diamonds everywhere. 2400.
All right.
The trucks are waiting.
The men are waiting. Everything--
[MEN SPEAKING IN GERMAN]
It's the fishing smack Santiago.
It leaves at 1 tomorrow night, here
from the end of La Medina. Third boat.
- Thank you. Thank you.
- And bring 15,000 francs in cash.
Remember, in cash.
[SPEAKING IN CANTONESE]
[SPEAKS INDISTINCTLY]
Cheerio.
CARL: Open up, Abdul.
- Yes, professor.
- Waiter?
- Yes, madame?
Will you ask Rick
if he'll have a drink with us?
He never drinks with customers.
Never. I have never seen it.
WOMAN:
What makes saloonkeepers so snobbish?
Perhaps if you told him...
...I ran the second-largest
banking house in Amsterdam.
Second largest?
That wouldn't impress Rick.
The leading banker in Amsterdam
is now the pastry chef in our kitchen.
We have something
to look forward to.
And his father is the bellboy.
Monsieur.
Excuse me.
I'm sorry, sir.
This is a private room.
Of all the nerve. Who do you think--?
I know there is gambling in there.
- You dare not keep me out.
RICK: Yes? What's the trouble?
I have been in every gambling room
between Honolulu and Berlin.
And if you think I'm going to be kept out
of a saloon like this...
...you're much mistaken.
Excuse me, please.
Hello, Rick.
Your cash is good at the bar.
What? Do you know who I am?
I do. You're lucky the bar is open to you.
This is outrageous!
I shall report it to The Angriff.
Watching you just now, one would
think you've been doing this all your life.
- What makes you think I haven't?
- Nothing.
- But when you first came, I thought--
- You thought what?
What right do I have to think?
May I?
Too bad about those two
German couriers, wasn't it?
They got a lucky break.
Yesterday they were just clerks...
...today they are the honored dead.
You are a very cynical person, Rick,
if you'll forgive me for saying so.
I forgive you.
- Will you have a drink with me?
- No.
I forgot, you never drink with--
I'll have another, please.
You despise me, don't you?
If I gave you any thought,
I probably would.
But why?
Do you object
to the kind of business I do?
But think of all those poor refugees who
must rot here if I didn't help them.
That's not so bad. Through ways of
my own, I provide them with exit visas.
For a price, Ugarte. For a price.
But think of all the poor devils
who can't meet Renault's price.
I get it for them for half.
Is that so parasitic?
I don't mind a parasite.
I object to a cut-rate one.
Well, after tonight I will be through
with the whole business.
And I'm leaving, finally,
this Casablanca.
Who did you bribe for your visa?
Renault or yourself?
Myself.
I found myself much more reasonable.
Look, Rick.
Know what this is?
Something that even you
have never seen.
Letters of transit signed
by General de Gaulle.
Cannot be rescinded.
Not even questioned.
One moment.
Tonight I'll be selling those
for more money than I ever dreamed of.
And then, addio, Casablanca.
I have many a friend in Casablanca,
but somehow...
...just because you despise me,
you are the only one I trust.
Will you keep these for me, please?
- For how long?
- Perhaps an hour. Perhaps a little longer.
- I don't want them here overnight.
- Don't be afraid of that.
Please keep them for me.
Thank you.
I knew I could trust you.
Waiter. I'll be expecting some people.
If anybody asks for me,
I'll be right here.
Rick...
...I hope you're more impressed
with me now.
If you'll forgive me, I'll share my
good luck with your roulette wheel.
Just a moment.
I heard a rumor those two German
couriers were carrying letters of transit.
Huh?
Oh. I've heard that
rumor too. Poor devils.
You're right, Ugarte.
I am a little more impressed with you.
[MUFFLED CLAPPING]
[SAM SINGS "KNOCK ON WOOD"]
- Say, who's got trouble?
- We got trouble
- How much trouble?
- Too much trouble
Well, now, don't you frown
Just knuckle down and knock on wood
- Who's unhappy?
- We're unhappy
- How unhappy?
- Too unhappy
Uh-oh, that won't do
When you are blue just knock on wood
- Who's unlucky?
- We're unlucky
- How unlucky?
- Too unlucky
But your luck will change
If you'll arrange to knock on wood
- Who's got nothing?
- We got nothing
- How much nothing?
- Too much nothing
Say, nothing's not an awful lot
But knock on wood
- Now who's happy?
- We're happy
- Just how happy?
- Very happy
That's the way we're gonna say
So knock on wood
- Now who's lucky?
- We're all lucky
- Just how lucky?
- Very lucky
Well, smile again and once again
Let's knock on wood
- Hello, Rick.
- Hello, Ferrari.
How's business at the Blue Parrot?
- Fine, but I'd like to buy your café.
- It's not for sale.
- You haven't heard my offer.
- It's not for sale at any price.
- What do you want for Sam?
- I don't buy or sell human beings.
Too bad.
That's Casablanca's leading commodity.
In refugees alone
we could make a fortune...
...if you'd work with me
in the black market.
Suppose you run your business
and let me run mine.
Suppose we ask Sam.
Maybe he'd like to make a change.
Suppose we do.
When will you realize
that in this world today...
...isolationism is no longer
a practical policy?
Sam, Ferrari wants you to work for him
at the Blue Parrot.
Oh, I like it fine here.
He'll double what I pay you.
I ain't got time to spend
what I make here.
Sorry.
The boss's private stock...
- ...because, Yvonne, I love you.
- Oh, shut up.
All right, all right. For you, I shut up,
because, Yvonne, I love you.
Uh-oh.
Oh, Monsieur Rick, Monsieur Rick.
Some Germans gave this check.
Is it all right?
Where were you last night?
That's so long ago,
I don't remember.
- Will I see you tonight?
- I never make plans that far ahead.
Give me another.
- Sascha, she's had enough.
- Don't listen to him. Fill it up.
Yvonne, I love you,
but he pays me.
- Rick, I'm tired of having you--
- Sascha, call a cab.
- We're gonna get your coat.
- Take your hands off me.
You're going home.
You've had a little too much to drink.
Hey, taxi.
Who do you think you are,
pushing me around?
I was a fool
to fall for a man like you.
Go with her, Sascha.
Be sure she gets home.
- And come right back.
- Yes, boss.
- Hello, Rick.
- Hello, Louis.
How extravagant you are,
throwing away women.
Someday they may be scarce.
I think now
I shall pay a call on Yvonne.
Maybe get her on the rebound.
When it comes to women,
you're a true democrat.
[SPEAKING IN FRENCH]
If he gets a word in,
it'll be a major Italian victory.
[PLANE ENGINE ROARING]
The plane to Lisbon.
You would like to be on it?
Why? What's in Lisbon?
The clipper to America.
I've often speculated on why
you don't return to America.
Did you abscond with the church funds?
Did you run off with a senator's wife?
I like to think you killed a man.
It's the romantic in me.
It's a combination of all three.
And what in heaven's name
brought you to Casablanca?
My health.
I came to Casablanca for the waters.
The waters? What waters?
We're in the desert.
- I was misinformed.
- Hm.
EMIL:
Excuse me, Monsieur Rick.
A gentleman inside
has won 20,000 francs...
...and the cashier
would like some money.
I'll get it from the safe.
I'm so upset, Rick. You know I--
Forget it, Emil. Mistakes like that
happen all the time.
EMIL:
I'm awfully sorry.
Rick, there will be some excitement
here tonight. An arrest in your café.
- Again?
- This is no ordinary arrest.
A murderer, no less.
If you're thinking of warning him, don't
put yourself out. He cannot escape.
- I stick my neck out for nobody.
- A wise foreign policy.
[SPEAKS IN FRENCH]
Could have made the arrest earlier,
at the Blue Parrot.
Out of my regard for you,
we're staging it here.
It will amuse your customers.
Our entertainment's enough.
We're to have an important guest
here tonight.
Major Strasser
of the Third Reich, no less.
We want him to be here
when we make the arrest.
A demonstration of the efficiency
of my administration.
RICK: I see.
And what's Strasser doing here?
He certainly didn't come here to witness
a demonstration of your efficiency.
- Perhaps not.
- Here.
- It shall not happen again.
- That's all right.
Louis, you got something on your mind.
Why don't you spill it.
How observant you are.
As a matter of fact,
I wanted to give you a word of advice.
Yeah?
- Have a brandy?
- Thank you.
There are many exit visas
sold in this café...
...but we know
that you've never sold one.
That is the reason
we permit you to remain open.
I thought it was because
I let you win at roulette.
That is another reason.
There is a man arrived in Casablanca
on his way to America.
He will offer a fortune to anyone
who'll furnish an exit visa.
- What's his name?
- Victor Laszlo.
Victor Laszlo?
Rick, that is the first time
I've seen you so impressed.
He's succeeded in impressing
half the world.
It's my duty to see that
he doesn't impress the other half.
Laszlo must never reach America.
He stays in Casablanca.
It'll be interesting
to see how he manages.
- Manages what?
- His escape.
- But I just told you--
- Stop it.
He escaped from
a concentration camp.
The Nazis have chased him
all over Europe.
- This is the end of the chase.
- Twenty thousand francs says it isn't.
Is that a serious offer?
I just paid out 20,
and I'd like to get it back.
Make it 10.
I'm only a poor corrupt official.
- Okay.
- Done.
No matter how clever he is, he still
needs an exit visa. Or I should say two.
- Why two?
- He is traveling with a lady.
- He'll take one.
- I think not. I've seen the lady.
And if he did not leave her
in Marseilles or Oran...
...he certainly won't leave her
in Casablanca.
Maybe he's not quite
as romantic as you are.
It doesn't matter.
There is no exit visa for him.
Whatever gave you the impression
that I might help Laszlo escape?
Because, my dear Ricky,
I suspect that under that cynical shell...
...you are at heart a sentimentalist.
Laugh if you will, but I happen
to be familiar with your record.
Let me point out just two items:
In 1935, you ran guns to Ethiopia.
In 1936, you fought in Spain
on the Loyalist side.
And got well paid for it
on both occasions.
The winning side would
have paid you much better.
- Maybe.
- Uh-huh.
It seems you're determined
to keep Laszlo here.
I have my orders.
I see. Gestapo spank.
My dear Ricky, you overestimate
the influence of the Gestapo.
I don't interfere with them,
and they don't interfere with me.
In Casablanca, I am master of my fate.
- I am--
- Major Strasser is here, sir.
- You were saying?
- Excuse me.
Carl, see that Major Strasser
gets a good table, close to the ladies.
I have already given him the best...
...knowing he is German
and would take it anyway.
Take him quietly.
Two guards at every door.
Yes, sir.
- Everything is ready, sir.
- Go ahead.
- Good evening, gentlemen.
- Good evening, captain.
- Won't you join us?
- Thank you.
- It's a pleasure to have you here, major.
- Champagne and a tin of caviar.
May I recommend Veuve Clicquot '26,
a good French wine.
- Thank you.
- Very well, sir.
- A very interesting club.
- Especially so tonight, major.
In a few minutes you'll see the arrest
of the man who murdered your couriers.
I expected no less, captain.
Monsieur Ugarte.
Oh. Yes?
- Will you please come with us?
- Certainly.
May I first please cash my chips?
[DEALER SPEAKING IN FRENCH]
Very lucky, huh?
Two thousand, please.
Thank you.
[SCREAMING]
Rick! Rick, help me!
- Don't be a fool. You can't get away.
- But, Rick, hide me. Do something!
Excellent, captain.
When they come for me,
I hope you'll be more of a help.
I stick my neck out for nobody.
I'm sorry there was a disturbance, folks,
but it's all over now.
Just sit down and have a good time.
Enjoy yourselves. All right, Sam.
Okay, boss.
[BAND PLAYING]
RENAULT:
Rick.
Rick, this is Major Heinrich Strasser
of the Third Reich.
- How do you do, Mr. Rick?
- How do you do?
You already know Herr Heinze
of the Third Reich.
Please join us, Mr. Rick.
We are very honored tonight.
Major Strasser is one of the reasons the
Third Reich enjoys the reputation it has.
You repeat Third Reich as though
you expected there to be others.
Well, personally, major,
I will take what comes.
Do you mind
if I ask you a few questions?
- Unofficially, of course.
- Make it official if you like.
- What is your nationality?
- I'm a drunkard.
And that makes Rick a citizen
of the world.
I was born in New York City,
if that'll help you any.
I understand you came here from Paris
at the time of the occupation.
There seems to be no secret
about that.
Are you one of those people...
...who cannot imagine the Germans
in their beloved Paris?
It's not particularly my beloved Paris.
Can you imagine us in London?
When you get there, ask me.
Diplomatist.
How about New York?
Well, there are
sections of New York, major...
...that I wouldn't advise
you to try to invade.
Uh-huh.
- Who do you think will win the war?
- I haven't the slightest idea.
Rick is completely neutral
about everything.
And that takes in the field
of women too.
You were not always
so carefully neutral.
We have a complete dossier on you.
"Richard Blaine, American. Age: 37.
Cannot return to his country."
The reason is a little vague.
We also know what you did in Paris.
And also we know why you left Paris.
Don't worry,
we're not going to broadcast it.
Are my eyes really brown?
You will forgive my curiosity,
Mr. Blaine. The point is...
...an enemy of the Reich
has come to Casablanca...
...and we are checking up on anybody
who can be of any help to us.
My interest in whether Victor Laszlo
stays or goes is purely a sporting one.
In this case you have no sympathy
for the fox?
Not particularly. I understand
the point of view of the hound too.
Laszlo published the foulest lies
in the Prague newspapers...
...until the day we marched in.
And even after that, he continued
to print scandal sheets in his cellar.
Of course, one must admit
he has great courage.
I admit he's clever. Three times
he slipped through our fingers.
In Paris he continued his activities.
We intend not to let it happen again.
Excuse me, gentlemen. Your business
is politics, mine is running a saloon.
Good evening, Mr. Blaine.
You see, major?
You have nothing to worry about Rick.
Perhaps.
Yes, monsieur?
- I reserved a table. Victor Laszlo.
- Yes, Monsieur Laszlo. Right this way.
Two Cointreaux, please.
I saw no one of Ugarte's description.
Victor, I feel somehow
we shouldn't stay here.
If we would walk out so soon
it would only call attention to us.
Perhaps Ugarte is in
some other part of the café.
Excuse me, but you look like a couple
who are on their way to America.
Well?
You'll find a market there for this ring.
I'm forced to sell it at a great sacrifice.
- Thank you, but I hardly think...
- Perhaps for the lady.
The ring is quite unique.
- Yes, I'm very interested.
- Good.
What is your name?
Berger, Norwegian.
At your service, sir.
Victor.
I'll meet you in a few minutes
at the bar.
We don't want the ring,
but thanks for showing it to us.
BERGER: Such a bargain.
But that is your decision?
I'm sorry, it is.
- Monsieur Laszlo, is it not?
- Yes?
I am Captain Renault,
prefect of police.
Yes, what is it you want?
Merely to welcome you to Casablanca
and wish you a pleasant stay.
It isn't often we have
so distinguished a visitor.
Thank you.
I hope you'll forgive me, captain.
The present French administration
hasn't always been so cordial.
May I present Miss Ilsa Lund.
I was told you were the most beautiful
woman ever to visit Casablanca.
That was a gross understatement.
You're very kind.
- Won't you join us?
- If you will permit me.
Oh, no, Emile, please. A bottle of your
best champagne. And put it on my bill.
- Captain, please.
- It's a game we play.
They put it on the bill,
I tear up the bill. It is very convenient.
Captain,
the boy who's playing the piano...
Somewhere I've seen him.
RENAULT: Sam?
- Yes.
He came from Paris with Rick.
Rick? Who is he?
Mademoiselle, you are in Rick's.
Rick is...
- Is what?
- Mademoiselle...
...he's the kind of man that,
well, if I were a woman...
...and I were not around,
I should be in love with Rick.
But what a fool I am talking to a
beautiful woman about another man.
Excuse me.
Major.
Mademoiselle Lund and Monsieur Laszlo,
may I present Major Strasser.
How do you do?
This is a pleasure
I have looked forward to.
I'm sure you'll excuse me
if I'm not gracious.
You see, Major Strasser,
I am a Czechoslovakian.
You were a Czechoslovakian. Now
you are a subject of the German Reich.
I have never accepted that privilege.
And I'm now on French soil.
I'd like to discuss some matters arising
from your presence on French soil.
This is hardly the time or place.
Then we shall state
another time and place.
Tomorrow at 10 in the prefect's office.
With mademoiselle.
Captain, I am under your authority.
Is it your order
that we come to your office?
Let us say it is my request.
That is a much more pleasant word.
- Very well.
- Mademoiselle.
Mademoiselle.
A very clever tactical retreat, major.
- This time they really mean to stop me.
- Victor, I'm afraid for you.
We've been in difficult places before,
haven't we?
[CLAPPING]
[SINGING IN SPANISH]
I must find out what Berger knows.
- Be careful.
- I will. Don't worry.
Monsieur Berger, the ring.
Could I see it again?
- Yes.
- Monsieur?
Champagne cocktail, please.
I recognize you from the news
photographs, Monsieur Laszlo.
In a concentration camp,
one is apt to lose a little weight.
We read five times that you were killed
in five different places.
As you see,
it was true every single time.
Thank heaven I found you, Berger.
I'm looking for a man by the name of
Ugarte. He's supposed to help me.
Ugarte cannot even help himself.
He's under arrest for murder.
He was arrested here tonight.
I see.
But we who are still free will do
all we can. We are organized.
Underground, like everywhere else.
Tomorrow night there is a meeting
at the Caverne du Bois.
If you will come--
SASCHA:
Monsieur.
Will you ask the piano player
to come over here?
MAN:
Very well, mademoiselle.
- How's the jewelry business, Berger?
- Not so good. Check, please.
Too bad you weren't here earlier.
We had quite a bit of excitement,
didn't we, Berger?
Yes. Excuse me, gentlemen.
- My bill.
- No. Two champagne cocktails. Please.
ILSA: Hello, Sam.
- Hello, Miss Ilsa.
I never expected to see you again.
It's been a long time.
Yes, ma'am.
A lot of water under the bridge.
- Some of the old songs, Sam.
- Yes, ma'am.
[PIANO PLAYING]
Where is Rick?
I don't know.
I ain't seen him all night.
- When will he be back?
- Not tonight no more. He ain't coming--
He went home.
- Does he always leave so early?
- Oh, he never--
Well, he's got a girl
up to the Blue Parrot.
Goes up there all the time.
You used to be
a much better liar, Sam.
Leave him alone, Miss Ilsa.
You're bad luck to him.
Play it once, Sam.
For old times' sake.
I don't know what you mean,
Miss Ilsa.
Play it, Sam.
Play "As Time Goes By."
I can't remember it, Miss Ilsa.
I'm a little rusty on it.
I'll hum it for you.
[HUMS]
["AS TIME GOES BY" PLAYS]
Sing it, Sam.
[SINGING "AS TIME GOES BY"]
You must remember this
A kiss is just a kiss
A sigh is just a sigh
The fundamental things apply
As time goes by
And when two lovers woo
They still say, "I love you"
On that you can rely
No matter what the future brings
As time goes by
Sam, I thought I told you
never to play--
Well, you were asking about Rick,
and here he is. May I present--
- Hello, Ilsa.
- Hello, Rick.
Oh, you've already met Rick,
mademoiselle? Then perhaps you also--
This is Mr. Laszlo.
- How do you do?
One hears a great deal about Rick
in Casablanca.
And about Victor Laszlo everywhere.
- Won't you join us for a drink?
- Rick never--
RICK: Thanks, I will.
- Well...
...a precedent is being broken. Emile.
- Interesting café. I congratulate you.
- I congratulate you.
- What for?
- Your work.
Thank you. I try.
We all try. You succeed.
She was asking about you
earlier, Rick...
...in a way that made me
extremely jealous.
I wasn't sure you were the same.
- Let's see, the last time we met--
- Was La Belle Aurore.
How nice. You remembered.
But, of course, that was the day
the Germans marched into Paris.
- Not an easy day to forget.
ILSA: No.
I remember every detail.
The Germans wore gray, you wore blue.
Yes. I put that dress away.
When the Germans march out
I'll wear it again.
Ricky, you're becoming quite human.
I suppose we have to thank you for that.
Ilsa, I don't wish to be the one
to say it, but it's late.
So it is.
We have a curfew in Casablanca.
It would never do for the chief of police
to be found drinking after hours.
LASZLO: I hope we didn't
overstay our welcome.
RICK:
Not at all.
- Your check, sir.
- It's my party.
Another precedent gone.
This has been a very interesting evening.
I'll call you a cab.
Gasoline rationing, time of night.
- We'll come again.
- Anytime.
- Say good night to Sam for me.
- I will.
There's still nobody in the world who
can play "As Time Goes By" like Sam.
He hasn't played it in a long time.
- Good night.
Night.
A very puzzling fellow, this Rick.
What sort is he?
I really can't say,
though I saw him quite often in Paris.
- Tomorrow at 10, at the prefect office.
- We'll be there.
- Good night.
Boss?
- Boss?
- Yeah?
- Boss, ain't you going to bed?
- Not right now.
Ain't you planning to go to bed
in the near future?
No.
- You ever going to bed?
- No.
Well, I ain't sleepy, either.
Good, then have a drink.
- Not me, boss.
- Then don't have a drink.
Boss, let's get out of here.
No, sir. I'm waiting for a lady.
Please, let's go.
Ain't nothing but trouble for you here.
She's coming back.
I know she's coming back.
We'll take the car and drive all night.
We'll get drunk. We'll go fishing,
stay away until she's gone.
- Shut up and go home, will you?
- No, sir, I'm staying right here.
They grab Ugarte, then she walks in.
Well, that's the way it goes.
One in, one out.
[PIANO PLAYING]
- Sam.
SAM: Yes, boss?
If it's December 1941 in Casablanca,
what time is it in New York?
What?
My watch stopped.
I bet they're asleep in New York.
I bet they're asleep all over America.
Of all the gin joints in all the towns
in all the world...
...she walks into mine.
- What's that you're playing?
- A little something of my own.
- Stop it. You know what I want to hear.
- No, I don't.
You played it for her.
You can play it for me.
- I don't think I can remember--
- If she can stand it, I can.
Play it.
Yes, boss.
["AS TIME GOES BY" PLAYS]
[CORK POPS]
Who are you really?
And what were you before?
What did you do,
and what did you think?
We said no questions.
Here's looking at you, kid.
A franc for your thoughts.
In America they'd bring only a penny.
I guess that's about all they're worth.
I'm willing to be overcharged. Tell me.
Well, I was wondering...
Yes?
Why I'm so lucky. Why I should
find you waiting for me to come along.
- Why there is no other man in my life?
- Uh-huh.
That's easy.
There was.
He's dead.
I'm sorry for asking.
I forgot we said no questions.
Well, only one answer can
take care of all our questions.
[YELLING IN FRENCH]
[MAN SPEAKING IN FRENCH
OVER LOUDSPEAKER]
Nothing can stop them now. Wednesday,
Thursday at the latest, they'll be in Paris.
Richard, they'll find out your record.
You won't be safe here.
I'm on their blacklist already.
Their roll of honor.
[SAM SINGS "AS TIME GOES BY"]
Moonlight and love songs
Never out of date
Hearts full of passion
Jealousy and hate
Woman needs man
And man must have his mate
That no one can deny
It's still the same old story
A fight for love and glory
A case of do or die
The world will always welcome lovers
As time goes by
Henri wants us to finish this bottle
and then three more.
Says he'll water his garden
with champagne...
...before he'll let the Germans drink it.
This sort of takes the sting out
of being occupied, doesn't it?
You said it.
Here's looking at you, kid.
[MAN SPEAKING IN GERMAN
OVER LOUDSPEAKER]
My German's a little rusty.
It's the Gestapo.
They say they expect to be
in Paris tomorrow.
They're telling us how to act
when they come marching in.
With the whole world crumbling,
we pick this time to fall in love.
It's pretty bad timing.
- Where were you, say, 10 years ago?
- 10 years ago?
Let's see.
Yes, I was having a brace put
on my teeth. Where were you?
Looking for a job.
[RUMBLING]
Was that cannon fire?
Or is it my heart pounding?
It's the new German 77th, and judging
by the sound, only about 35 miles away.
And getting closer every minute.
Here, here, drink up.
We'll never finish the other three.
Them Germans will be here pretty soon,
and they'll come looking for you.
And don't forget,
there's a price on your head.
I left a note in my apartment.
They'll know where to find me.
It's strange.
- I know so very little about you.
- I know very little about you.
Just the fact that
you had your teeth straightened.
Be serious, darling. You are in danger.
You must leave Paris.
No, we must leave.
Yes, of course. We.
The train for Marseilles leaves at 5:00.
I'll pick you up at your hotel at 4:30.
No, no. Not at my hotel. I...
I have things to do in the city
before I leave.
I'll meet you at the station.
All right, at a quarter to 5.
Why don't we get married
in Marseilles?
[STAMMERS]
That's too far ahead to plan.
Yes. I guess it is too far ahead.
Let's see... What about the engineer?
Why can't he marry us on the train?
Oh, darling...
Why not? The captain on a ship can.
It doesn't seem fair that--
Hey...
Hey, what's wrong, kid?
I love you so much.
And I hate this war so much.
It's a crazy world.
Anything can happen.
If you shouldn't get away...
I mean if--
If something should keep us apart...
...wherever they put you...
...and wherever I'll be,
I want you to know that I...
[RUMBLING]
Kiss me.
Kiss me as if it were the last time.
[YELLING IN FRENCH]
All aboard! The last train
leaving in three minutes.
Where is she?
Have you seen her?
I can't find her.
She checked out of the hotel.
But this note came just after you left.
[WHISTLE BLOWS]
That's the last call, Mr. Richard.
Do you hear me?
Come on, Mr. Richard.
Let's get out of here. Come on.
[TRAIN WHISTLE BLOWS]
[PIANO STOPS]
- Rick, I have to talk to you.
- Uh-huh.
I saved my first drink
to have with you. Here.
- No, Rick. Not tonight.
- Especially tonight.
Why did you have to come to
Casablanca? There are other places.
I wouldn't have come
if I'd known you were here.
Believe me, Rick, it's true.
I didn't know.
It's funny about your voice,
how it hasn't changed. I can still hear it.
"Richard, dear,
I'll go with you anyplace.
- We'll get on a train and never stop."
- Don't, Rick.
I can understand how you feel.
You understand how I feel.
How long was it we had, honey?
- I didn't count the days.
- Well, I did.
Every one of them.
Mostly I remember the last one.
The wild finish. A guy standing
on a station platform in the rain...
...with a comical look on his face...
...because his insides
have been kicked out.
Can I tell you a story, Rick?
Does it got a wild finish?
I don't know the finish yet.
Go on, tell it. Maybe one'll come
to you as you go along.
It's about a girl who had just come
to Paris from her home in Oslo.
At the house of some friends...
...she met a man about whom
she'd heard her whole life.
A very great and courageous man.
He opened up for her a whole
beautiful world...
...full of knowledge
and thoughts and ideals.
Everything she knew
or ever became was because of him.
And she looked up to him...
...and worshiped him...
...with a feeling
she supposed was love.
Yes, that's very pretty.
I heard a story once. In fact,
I've heard a lot of stories in my time.
They went along with the sound
of a tinny piano...
...playing in the parlor downstairs.
"Mister, I met a man once
when I was a kid," they'd always begin.
I guess neither one of our stories
is very funny.
Tell me...
...who was it you left me for?
Was it Laszlo,
or were there others in between...
...or aren't you the kind that tells?
[DOOR CLOSES]
I strongly suspect that Ugarte left the
letters of transit with Mr. Blaine.
I would suggest you search
the café immediately.
If Rick has the letters, he's too smart
to let you find them there.
You give him credit
for too much cleverness.
My impression was he's just
another blundering American.
We mustn't underestimate
American blundering.
I was with them when they blundered
into Berlin in 1918.
As to Laszlo,
we want him watched 24 hours a day.
It may interest you to know that at
this very moment he's on his way here.
There is nothing we can do.
I'm delighted to see you.
Did you have a good night's rest?
I slept very well.
Strange. Nobody's supposed
to sleep well in Casablanca.
- May we proceed?
- With pleasure. Won't you sit down?
Thank you.
Laszlo, we will not mince words.
You're an escaped prisoner of the Reich.
So far you have been fortunate
in eluding us.
You have reached Casablanca.
It is my duty to see
that you stay in Casablanca.
Whether or not you will succeed
is problematic.
Not at all. Renault's signature
is necessary on every visa.
Captain, is it possible that Laszlo
will receive a visa?
I'm afraid not. My regrets, monsieur.
Well, perhaps I shall like it
in Casablanca.
STRASSER:
And mademoiselle?
- You needn't be concerned about me.
- Is that all you wish to tell us?
Don't be in such a hurry.
You have all the time in the world.
You may be
in Casablanca indefinitely.
Or you may leave
for Lisbon tomorrow.
- On one condition.
- And that is?
You know the leader of the underground
movement in Paris, in Prague...
...Brussels, Amsterdam...
...Oslo, Belgrade, Athens...
- Even Berlin.
- Yes, even in Berlin.
If you will furnish me with their names
and whereabouts...
...you'll have your visa in the morning.
And the honor of having served
the Third Reich.
I was in a German concentration camp
for a year.
- That's honor enough for a lifetime.
- You will give us the names?
If I didn't give them to you
in a concentration camp...
...where you had more persuasive
methods at your disposal...
...I certainly won't
give them to you now.
And what if you track down
these men and kill them?
What if you murdered all of us?
From every corner of Europe, hundreds,
thousands would rise to take our places.
Even Nazis can't kill that fast.
Herr Laszlo, you have a reputation for
eloquence which I can now understand.
But in one aspect you are mistaken.
You said the enemies
of the Reich could all be replaced.
But there is one exception.
No one could take your place
if anything unfortunate...
...should occur to you
while you were trying to escape.
You won't dare
to interfere with me here.
This is still unoccupied France.
Any violation of neutrality
would reflect on Captain Renault.
- Monsieur, insofar as it is in my power.
- Thank you.
By the way, monsieur, last night
you evinced an interest in Signor Ugarte.
- Yes?
- I believe you have a message for him?
Nothing important.
But may I speak to him now?
You would find the conversation
a trifle one-sided.
Signor Ugarte is dead.
I'm making out the report now.
We haven't quite decided
whether he committed suicide...
...or died trying to escape.
- Are you quite finished with us?
- For the time being.
Good day.
Undoubtedly, their next step will
be to the black market.
Excuse me, captain.
Another visa problem has come up.
- Show her in.
- Yes, sir.
Sorry, monsieur, we were never
to handle the police.
- This is a job for Signor Ferrari.
- Ferrari?
It can be most helpful
to know Signor Ferrari.
He pretty near has a monopoly
on the black market here.
You will find him at the Blue Parrot.
MAN:
Thanks.
FERRARI:
Don't be too downhearted.
Perhaps you can
come to terms with Renault.
Thank you very much, signor.
RICK: Hello, Ferrari.
- Good morning, Rick.
The bus is in.
I'll take my shipment with me.
I'll have it sent over.
Have a drink with me.
I never drink in the morning.
And every time you send my
shipment over it's a little short.
Carrying charges, my boy.
Carrying charges.
Here, sit down.
There is something I want
to talk over with you, anyhow.
Bourbon.
The news about Ugarte
upsets me very much.
You're a fat hypocrite. You don't feel
any sorrier for Ugarte than I do.
Of course not. What upsets me
is that Ugarte is dead...
...and no one knows where
those letters are.
Practically no one.
If I had those letters,
I could make a fortune.
So could I,
and I'm a poor businessman.
I have a proposition
for whoever has those letters.
I'll handle the entire transaction.
Get rid of the letters, take all the risk,
for a small percentage.
And the carrying charges?
Naturally there will be a few
incidental expenses.
That's my proposition
for whoever has those letters.
I'll tell him when he comes in.
Rick, I think you know
where those letters are.
You're in good company. Renault
and Strasser probably think so too.
That's why I came here. To give
them a chance to ransack my place.
Rick, don't be a fool. Take me into
your confidence. You need a partner.
Excuse me, I'll be getting back.
LASZLO:
Morning.
Signor Ferrari
is the fat gent at the table.
MAN: You will not find a treasure
like this in all Morocco.
Only 700 francs.
- You're being cheated.
- Doesn't matter, thank you.
For friends of Rick's
we have a small discount.
Did I say 700 francs?
You can have it for 200.
I'm sorry I was in no condition to receive
you when you called on me last night.
Doesn't matter.
For special friends of Rick's
we have a special discount. 100 francs.
Your story had me a little confused.
Or maybe it was the bourbon.
I have some tablecloths, napkins--
- Thank you. I'm really not interested.
- Please, one minute.
Why did you come back? To tell me why
you ran out on me at the railway station?
Yes.
Well, you can tell me now.
I'm reasonably sober.
I don't think I will, Rick.
Why not? After all, I got stuck with
a railway ticket.
I think I'm entitled to know.
Last night I saw
what has happened to you.
The Rick I knew in Paris,
I could tell him, he'd understand.
But the one who looked at me
with such hatred...
I'll be leaving Casablanca soon.
We'll never see each other again.
We knew very little about each other
when we were in love in Paris.
If we leave it that way...
...maybe we'll remember
those days and not Casablanca.
Not last night.
Did you run out on me because
you knew what it would be like?
Hiding from the police,
running away all the time?
You can believe that if you want to.
Well, I'm not running away anymore.
I'm settled now.
Above a saloon, it's true...
...but walk up a flight...
...I'll be expecting you.
All the same,
someday you'll lie to Laszlo.
You'll be there.
No, Rick.
No. You see, Victor Laszlo
is my husband.
And was,
even when I knew you in Paris.
I was just telling Monsieur Laszlo that
unfortunately I'm not able to help him.
You see, my dear,
word has gone around.
As leader of all illegal activities in
Casablanca...
...I am influential and respected.
But it would not be worth my life
to do anything for Monsieur Laszlo.
You, however, are a different matter.
Signor Ferrari thinks it might just be
possible to get an exit visa for you.
- You mean for me to go on alone?
- And only alone.
I'll stay here and keep on trying.
I'm sure in a little while--
Might as well be frank, monsieur.
It would take a miracle to get you out.
The Germans have outlawed miracles.
We are only interested in two visas.
- Please, Ilsa, don't be hasty.
- No, Victor.
You two will want to discuss this.
Excuse me. I'll be at the bar.
No, Ilsa.
I won't let you stay here.
You must get to America. Believe me,
somehow I will get out and join you.
But if the situation were different...
...if I had to stay
and there were only visa for one...
...would you take it?
Yes, I would.
Yes, I see.
When I had trouble getting out of Lille,
why didn't you leave me there?
When I was sick
in Marseilles for two weeks...
...and you were in danger every minute,
why didn't you leave me then?
I meant to,
but something always held me up.
I love you very much, Ilsa.
Your secret will be safe with me.
Ferrari is waiting for our answer.
Not more than 50 francs.
We've decided, Signor Ferrari.
For the present we will go on looking
for two visas. Thank you very much.
Well, good luck, but be careful.
- You know you're being shadowed?
- Of course. It becomes an instinct.
I observe that you, in one respect,
are a very fortunate man.
I am moved to make one more
suggestion. Why, I do not know.
Because it cannot possibly profit me.
Have you heard about Ugarte
and the letters of transit?
Yes, something.
Those letters were not found on Ugarte
when they arrested him.
- You know where they are?
- Not for sure.
But I'd guess that Ugarte
left those letters with Monsieur Rick.
Rick?
A difficult customer, that Rick.
One never knows what he'll do or why.
But it is worth a chance.
Thank you very much.
Good day.
Goodbye. Thank you for your coffee.
I shall miss that
when we leave Casablanca.
Gracious of you to share it with me.
Good day, mademoiselle.
- Monsieur.
- Good day.
[PIANO PLAYING]
- Here's to you, sir.
- Good luck.
- I'd better be going.
- My check, please.
I have to warn you, sir. This is
a dangerous place. Full of vultures.
Vultures everywhere.
Thanks for everything.
- Goodbye.
- It has been a pleasure to meet you.
I'm sorry.
Monsieur Rick, you are getting
to be your best customer.
Well, drinking.
I'm very pleased with you.
You're beginning
to live like a Frenchman.
That was some going-over
your men gave my place.
We barely got cleaned up
in time to open.
I told Strasser he wouldn't
find the letters here.
But I told my men
to be especially destructive.
You know how
that impresses Germans.
Rick, have you got
those letters of transit?
Louis, are you Pro-Vichy
or Free French?
Serves me right for asking a direct
question. The subject is closed.
- It looks like you're a little late.
- Huh?
So Yvonne's gone over to the enemy.
Who knows? In her own way, she
may constitute an entire second front.
I think it's time for me to flatter
Strasser a little. I'll see you later.
Sascha!
French 75s.
Put up a whole row of them, Sascha.
Starting here and ending here.
We will begin with two.
[SPEAKING IN FRENCH]
What did you say?
Would you kindly repeat it?
- What I said is none of your business.
- I'll make it my business.
I don't like disturbances in my place.
Either lay off politics or get out.
You see, captain?
The situation is not as under control
as you believe.
We try to cooperate
with your government.
But we cannot regulate
the feelings of our people.
Captain, are you certain
which side you're on?
I have no conviction,
if that's what you mean.
I blow with the wind...
...and the prevailing wind
happens to be from Vichy.
And if it should change?
Surely the Reich doesn't admit
that possibility?
We are concerned
about more than Casablanca.
We know that every French province
in Africa is honeycombed with traitors.
Waiting for their chance.
Waiting perhaps for a leader.
A leader? Like Laszlo?
Mm-hm. I have been thinking.
It's too dangerous to let him go,
it may be too dangerous to let him stay.
I see what you mean.
[SPEAKING IN GERMAN]
Thank you, Carl.
Sit down. Have a brandy with us.
To celebrate our leaving
for America tomorrow.
Thank you very much.
I thought you would ask me,
so I brought the good brandy...
...and a third glass.
At last the day's came!
Frau Leuchtag and I
are speaking nothing but English now.
So we should feel at home
when we get to America.
A very nice idea.
- To America.
To America.
[SPEAKS IN GERMAN]
What watch?
- Ten watch.
- Such much?
You will get along beautifully
in America.
How is lady luck treating you?
Oh, too bad.
You'll find him over there.
- Monsieur Rick?
- Yes?
- Could I speak to you, please?
- How'd you get in? You're underage.
- I came with Captain Renault.
- I should have known.
My husband is with me too.
He is? Captain Renault's getting
broad-minded. Sit down.
Have a drink?
- No, of course not. You mind if I do?
- Oh, no.
Monsieur Rick,
what kind of a man is Captain Renault?
Like any other man, only more so.
No, I mean...
...is he trustworthy?
Is his word--?
Just a minute.
Who told you to ask me that?
He did. Captain Renault did.
I thought so. Where's your husband?
At the roulette table,
trying to win enough for our exit visas.
Oh, of course he's losing.
- How long have you been married?
- Eight weeks.
We come from Bulgaria.
Things are very bad there.
The devil has the people
by the throat.
So Jan and I, we...
We do not want our children
to grow up in such a country.
- So you decided to go to America.
- Yes.
But we haven't much money...
...and traveling is so expensive
and difficult.
It was much more than we thought
to get here.
And then Captain Renault sees us,
and he is so kind, he wants to help us.
Yes, I'll bet.
He tells me he can give us an exit visa.
But we have no money.
- Does he know that?
- Yes.
- And he's still willing to give you a visa?
- And you want to know...?
- Will he keep his word?
He always has.
Oh...
Monsieur...
...you are a man.
If someone loved you very much...
...so that your happiness was the only
thing that she wanted in the world...
...and she did a bad thing
to make certain of it...
- ...could you forgive her?
- Nobody ever loved me that much.
And he never knew, and the girl kept
this bad thing locked in her heart...
...that would be all right,
wouldn't it?
- You want my advice?
- Yes, please.
Go back to Bulgaria.
Oh, but if you knew what it means to us
to leave Europe, to get to America...
Oh, but if Jan should find out.
He is such a boy.
In many ways
I am so much older than he is.
Yes, well, everybody in Casablanca
has problems.
- Yours may work out. You'll excuse me.
- Thank you, monsieur.
- Good evening.
You see? Here we are again.
I take that
as a great compliment to Sam.
I suppose he means to you
Paris of happier days.
He does. Could we
have a table close to him?
And as far away
from Major Strasser as possible.
The geography may be
a little difficult to arrange.
- Paul, table 30.
PAUL: Yes, sir.
Right this way, if you please.
I'll have Sam play "As Time Goes By."
I believe that's your favorite tune.
Thank you.
["AS TIME GOES BY" PLAYS]
- Two cognacs, please.
- Cognac.
[SPEAKING IN FRENCH]
Do you wish to place another bet, sir?
No. No, I guess not.
Have you tried 22 tonight?
I said 22.
[SPEAKING IN FRENCH]
Leave it there.
Cash it in and don't come back.
Are you sure this place is honest?
Honest? As honest as the day is long.
How are we doing tonight?
A couple of thousand less
than I thought there would be.
Monsieur Rick...
I-- Oh...
He's just a lucky guy.
Monsieur Rick,
may I get you a cup of coffee?
- No, thanks, Carl.
- Monsieur Rick...
Captain Renault, may I--?
Not here.
Come to my office in the morning.
We'll do everything businesslike.
- We'll be there at 6.
- I'll be there at 10.
I'm very happy for both of you.
Still, it's very strange that you won.
Well, maybe not so strange.
- I'll see you in the morning.
- Thank you, Captain Renault.
No!
[SPEAKING INDISTINCTLY]
Boss, you've done a beautiful thing.
Go away, you crazy Russian.
As I suspected.
You're a rank sentimentalist.
Yeah? Why?
Why do you interfere
with my little romances?
Put it down as a gesture to love.
Well, I'll forgive you this time.
But I'll be in tomorrow night
with a breathtaking blond.
And it'll make me very happy
if she loses.
Mm-hm.
Mr. Blaine,
I wonder if I could talk to you.
- Go ahead.
- Well, isn't there some other place?
It's rather confidential,
what I have to say.
- In my office.
- Right.
You must know it's very important
I get out of Casablanca.
It's my privilege to be one of the leaders
of a great movement.
You know what I've been doing.
You know what it means to the work,
to the lives of thousands of people...
...that I reach America
and continue my work.
I'm not interested in politics.
The problems of the world
are not in my department.
I'm a saloonkeeper.
My friends in the underground tell me
that you have quite a record.
You ran guns to Ethiopia.
You fought against
the fascists in Spain.
What of it?
Isn't it strange you're always
fighting on the side of the underdog?
Yes, I found that
a very expensive hobby.
But then I never was
much of a businessman.
Are you enough of a businessman to
appreciate an offer of 100,000 francs?
- I appreciate it, but I don't accept it.
- 200,000.
My friend, you could make it
a million francs or three.
My answer would still be the same.
There must be some reason
why you won't let me.
There is.
I suggest that you ask your wife.
- I beg your pardon?
- I said, ask your wife.
- My wife?
- Yes.
[SINGING "DIE WACHT AM RHEIN"]
Play "La Marseillaise."
Play it!
[SINGING "LA MARSEILLAISE"]
Vive la France!
See what I mean? If Laszlo's presence in
a café can inspire this demonstration...
...what more will his presence
in Casablanca bring on?
I advise that this place
be shut up at once.
- But everybody's having a good time.
- Yes, much too good a time.
The place is to be closed.
- But I have no excuse to close it.
- Find one.
[WHISTLE BLOWS]
Everybody is to leave immediately.
This café is closed until further notice.
Clear the room at once.
How can you close me up?
I'm shocked, shocked to find that
gambling is going on in here.
- Your winnings, sir.
- Thank you.
Everybody out at once.
After this disturbance it is not safe
for Laszlo to stay in Casablanca.
This morning you implied it wasn't safe
to leave Casablanca.
That is also true, except for one
destination: occupied France.
- Occupied France?
- Under safe conduct from me.
Of what value is that?
You may recall what German guarantees
have been worth in the past.
- There are two other alternatives for him.
- What are they?
The French authorities
may find a reason...
...to put him
in the concentration camp here.
The other alternative?
My dear,
perhaps you have already observed...
...that in Casablanca
human life is cheap.
Good night, mademoiselle.
- What happened with Rick?
- We'll discuss it later.
Our faithful friend is still there.
Please don't go
to the underground meeting tonight.
I must.
Besides, it isn't often that a man gets
to display heroics before his wife.
Don't joke. After Major Strasser's
warning tonight, I'm frightened.
Tell you the truth,
I'm frightened too.
Shall I remain here
in a hotel room, hiding?
Or shall I carry on the best I can?
Whatever I'd say,
you would carry on.
Victor, why don't you tell me
about Rick? What did you find out?
- Apparently he has the letters.
- Yes?
But no intention of selling them.
You'd think if sentiment
wouldn't persuade him, money would.
Did he give any reason?
- He suggested I ask you.
- Ask me?
Yes, he said, "Ask your wife."
I don't know why he said that.
Well, our friend outside will think
we've retired by now.
I'll be going in a few minutes.
- Ilsa, I...
- Yes?
When I was
in the concentration camp...
...were you lonely in Paris?
Yes, Victor, I was.
I know how it is to be lonely.
Is there anything you wish to tell me?
No, Victor, there isn't.
I love you very much, my dear.
Yes.
Yes, I know.
Victor, whatever I do,
will you believe that I...?
You don't even have to say it.
I'll believe.
Good night, dear.
Good night.
- Victor.
- Yes, dear?
Be careful.
Of course I'll be careful.
Well, you are in
pretty good shape, Herr Rick.
How long can I afford to stay closed?
Two weeks, maybe three.
Maybe I won't have to.
A bribe has worked before.
In the meantime,
everybody stays on salary.
Thank you, Herr Rick.
Sascha will be happy to hear it.
I owe him money.
- You finish locking up, will you, Carl?
- I will.
- Then I am going to the meeting--
- Don't tell me where you're going.
I won't.
Good night.
Good night, Mr. Rick.
- How did you get in?
- The stairs from the street.
I told you this morning you'd come
around, but this is ahead of schedule.
Well, won't you sit down?
- Richard, I had to see you.
- "Richard" again. We're back in Paris.
Your visit isn't connected
by any chance with the letters of transit?
Seems as long as I have those letters
I'll never be lonely.
Ask any price you want,
but you must give me the letters.
I went all through that
with your husband. It's no deal.
I know how you feel about me...
...but put your feelings aside
for something more important.
I have to hear again
what a great man your husband is...
...what an important cause
he's fighting for?
It was your cause too.
In your own way, you were fighting
for the same thing.
I'm not fighting for anything
anymore except myself.
I'm the only cause I'm interested in.
Richard.
We loved each other once. If those
days meant anything at all to you--
I wouldn't bring up Paris if I were you.
It's poor salesmanship.
Listen to me. If you knew what really
happened, if you only knew the truth--
I wouldn't believe you
no matter what you said.
You'd say anything now
to get what you want.
You want to feel sorry for yourself,
don't you?
With so much at stake
all you can think of is your feelings.
One woman has hurt you...
...and you take your revenge
on the rest of the world.
You're a coward and a weakling.
No. Oh, Richard. I'm sorry.
I'm sorry, but you are our last hope.
If you don't help us,
Victor Laszlo will die in Casablanca.
What of it?
I'm going to die in Casablanca.
It's a good spot for it.
Now, if you'll--
All right.
I tried to reason with you.
I tried everything.
Now, I want those letters.
- Get them for me.
- I don't have to. I got them right here.
Put them on the table.
No.
For the last time,
put them on the table.
If Laszlo and the cause mean so much
to you, you won't stop at anything.
All right,
I'll make it easier for you.
Go ahead and shoot.
You'll be doing me a favor.
Richard...
...I tried to stay away.
I thought I would never see you again.
That you were out of my life.
The day you left Paris...
...if you knew what I went through.
If you knew how much I loved you.
How much I still love you.
And then?
It wasn't long after we were married
that Victor went back to Czechoslovakia.
They needed him in Prague, but there
the Gestapo were waiting for him.
Just a two-line item in the paper:
"Victor Laszlo apprehended.
Sent to concentration camp."
I was frantic.
For months I tried to get word.
Then it came.
He was dead.
Shot trying to escape.
I was lonely.
I had nothing, not even hope.
Then I met you.
Why weren't you honest with me?
Why'd you keep your marriage a secret?
It wasn't my secret, Richard.
Victor wanted it that way.
Not even our closest friends
knew about our marriage.
That was his way of protecting me.
I knew so much about his work.
If the Gestapo found out I was his wife
it would be dangerous for me...
...and for those working with us.
And when did you first find out
he was alive?
Just before you and I
were to leave Paris together.
A friend came and told me
that Victor was alive.
They were hiding him in a freight car
on the outskirts of Paris.
He was sick. He needed me.
I wanted to tell you,
but I didn't dare.
I knew you wouldn't have left Paris,
and the Gestapo would have caught you.
Well...
...well, you know the rest.
Well, it's still a story
without an ending.
What about now?
Now?
I don't know.
I know that I'll never have the strength
to leave you again.
And Laszlo?
You'll help him now, Richard, won't you?
You'll see that he gets out.
Then he'll have his work.
All that he's been living for.
All except one.
He won't have you.
I can't fight it anymore.
I ran away from you once.
I can't do it again.
Oh, I don't know
what's right any longer.
You have to think for both of us.
For all of us.
All right. I will.
Here's looking at you, kid.
I wish I didn't love you so much.
- I think we lost them.
- Yes.
I'm afraid they caught
some of the others.
Come inside.
Come, Mr. Laszlo,
I will help you immediately.
LASZLO:
Thank you.
RICK:
Carl, what happened?
The police break up our meeting,
Herr Rick.
We escaped at the last moment.
- Come up here a minute.
- Yes, I come.
Turn out the light in the rear entrance.
It might attract the police.
- But Sascha always puts out that light.
- Tonight he forgot.
Yes, I come. I will do it.
- I want you to take Miss Lund home.
- Yes, sir.
It's nothing, just a little cut.
We had to get through a window.
This might come in handy.
Thank you.
- Had a close one, eh?
- Yes, rather.
Don't you sometimes wonder
if it's worth all this?
I mean, what you're fighting for.
We might as well question
why we breathe.
If we stop breathing, we'll die.
If we stop fighting our enemies,
the world will die.
What of it?
Then it'll be out of its misery.
You know how you sound,
Monsieur Blaine?
Like a man
who's trying to convince himself...
...of something
he doesn't believe in his heart.
Each of us has a destiny.
For good, or for evil.
- I get the point.
- I wonder if you do.
I wonder if you know that you're trying
to escape from yourself...
...and that you'll never succeed.
You seem to know
all about my destiny.
I know a good deal more
about you than you suspect.
I know that you're in love
with a woman.
It's perhaps a strange circumstance...
...that we both should be in love
with the same woman.
The first evening
I came into this café...
...I knew there was something
between you and Ilsa.
Since no one is to blame...
...I demand no explanation.
I ask only one thing.
You won't give me the letters of transit.
All right.
But I want my wife to be safe.
I ask you as a favor...
...to use the letters
to take her away from Casablanca.
You love her that much?
Apparently you think of me only
as the leader of a cause.
Well, I am also a human being.
Yes, I love her that much.
[CLATTERING]
- Monsieur Laszlo?
- Yes?
You'll come with us.
We have a warrant for your arrest.
On what charge?
Captain Renault will discuss that
with you later.
It seems that destiny
has taken a hand.
You haven't any proof, and you know it.
This isn't Germany or occupied France.
All you can do is fine him
and give him 30 days.
You might as well let him go now.
I'd advise you not to be too interested
in what happens to Laszlo.
If you were to help him escape--
What makes you think
I'd stick my neck out for Laszlo?
Because, one,
you bet 10,000 francs he'd escape.
Two, you've got the letters of transit.
Don't bother to deny it.
And you might do it simply
because you don't like Strasser's looks.
As a matter of fact,
I don't either.
They're all excellent reasons.
Don't count too much
on my friendship.
In this matter I'm powerless.
Besides, I might lose the 10,000 francs.
You're not very subtle,
but you are effective. I get the point.
Yes, I have the letters.
But I intend using them myself.
I'm leaving Casablanca
on tonight's plane. The last plane.
And I'm taking a friend with me.
One you'll appreciate.
- What friend?
- Ilsa Lund.
That ought to put your mind to rest
about my helping Laszlo escape.
The last man I want to see in America.
You didn't come here to tell me this.
You have the letters of transit.
You can fill in your name and hers
and leave anytime you please.
Why are you still interested
in what happens to Laszlo?
I'm not. But I am interested
in what happens to Ilsa and me.
We have a legal right to go,
that's true...
...but people have been held
in Casablanca...
...in spite of their legal rights.
What makes you think
we want to hold you?
Ilsa is Laszlo's wife.
She probably knows things
that Strasser would like to know.
Louis, I'll make a deal with you.
Instead of this petty charge against him,
you could get something big...
...something that would chuck him
in a concentration camp for years...
- Be quite a feather in your cap, right?
- Certainly.
Germany--
Vichy would be very grateful.
Then release him.
You be at my place a half-hour
before the plane leaves.
I'll have Laszlo come there
to pick up the letters...
...and that'll give you grounds
to make the arrest.
You get him, and we get away.
To the Germans,
that last will be just a minor annoyance.
There's still something about this
I don't quite understand.
Miss Lund, she is very beautiful, yes...
...but you were never interested
in any woman.
- She isn't just any woman.
- I see.
How do I know you'll keep
your end of the bargain?
I'll make the arrangements now
with Laszlo in the visitor's pen.
I'm gonna miss you.
You're the only one in Casablanca
who has less scruples than I.
Oh, thanks.
Go ahead, Ricky.
Call off your watchdogs
when you let him go.
I don't want them around
this afternoon.
I'm taking no chances, Louis,
not even with you.
FERRARI: Should we draw up papers,
or is a handshake good enough?
Certainly not good enough.
But since I'm in a hurry, it'll have to do.
To get out of Casablanca and
go to America... You're a lucky man.
My agreement with Sam is that he gets
25 percent of the profits. That still goes.
I happen to know he gets 10 percent.
But he's worth 25.
Abdul, Carl and Sascha,
they stay with the place or I don't sell.
Of course.
Rick's wouldn't be Rick's without them.
Well, so long.
Don't forget you owe Rick's
100 cartons of American cigarettes.
I shall remember to pay it to myself.
[STEPPING]
[KNOCKING]
RICK:
You're late.
I was informed when Laszlo
left the hotel so I knew I'd be on time.
- I asked you to tie up your watchdogs.
- He won't be followed here.
This place will never be
the same without you.
I know what you mean. But I've spoken
to Ferrari. You'll still win at roulette.
- Is everything ready?
- I have the letters right here.
When we searched the place,
where were they?
Sam's piano.
Serves me right for not being musical.
[TIRES SQUEALING]
Here they are.
You better wait in my office.
Here.
Victor thinks I'm leaving with him.
Haven't you told him?
Not yet.
But you were able to
arrange everything?
Everything is quite all right.
We'll tell him at the airport.
The less time to think, the easier.
Please trust me.
Yes, I will.
- I don't know how to thank you.
- Save it. We've still lots of things to do.
LASZLO: I brought the money.
- Keep it, you'll need it in America.
- But we made a deal.
- Never mind that.
- You won't have any trouble in Lisbon?
- No. It's all arranged.
Good. I've got the letters here,
made out in blank.
All you have to do is fill
in the signatures.
RENAULT:
Victor Laszlo.
Victor Laszlo, you're under arrest.
The charge of
accessory to the murder...
...of the couriers
from whom the letters were stolen.
You're surprised about my friend Ricky?
The explanation is simple.
Love, it seems,
has triumphed over virtue. Thank--
Not so fast, Louis. Nobody is going
to be arrested. Not for a while yet.
- Have you lost your mind?
- I have. Sit down.
- Put that gun down.
- I don't want to shoot you...
...but I will if you take one more step.
Under the circumstances,
I will sit down.
- Keep your hands on the table.
- I wonder if you realize what this means.
I do. We've got time
to discuss that later.
Call off your watchdogs, you said.
Just the same, call the airport
and let me hear you tell them.
And remember,
this gun is pointed right at your heart.
That is my least vulnerable spot.
- Hello? Is that the airport?
- Huh?
This is Captain Renault speaking.
There'll be two letters of transit
for the Lisbon plane.
There's to be no trouble about them.
Good.
Hello? Hello?
[BUZZING]
My car, quickly!
[SPEAKS IN GERMAN]
This is Major Strasser.
Have a squad of police meet me
at the airport at once.
At once, do you hear?
MAN:
Hello, radio tower?
Lisbon plane taking off in 10 minutes,
east runway.
Visibility, 1 1/2 miles.
Light ground fog.
Depth of fog approximately 500.
Ceiling unlimited. Thank you.
Have your man go with Laszlo
and take care of his luggage.
Certainly, Rick, anything you say.
Find Laszlo's luggage.
Put it on the plane.
Yes, sir.
This way, please.
If you don't mind, fill in the names.
That'll make it more official.
You think of everything, don't you?
And the names are
Mr. and Mrs. Victor Laszlo.
- But why my name, Richard?
- Because you're getting on that plane.
I don't understand.
What about you?
I'm staying with him
till the plane gets away.
No. What has happened?
Last night you said--
Last night
we said a great many things.
You said
I was to do the thinking for us.
I've done a lot of it since then.
It adds up to one thing:
You're getting on that plane
with Victor where you belong.
- Richard, no--
- Now, you've got to listen to me.
Any idea what you'd have
to look forward to if you stayed here?
Chances are we'd both wind up
in a concentration camp. True, Louis?
I'm afraid Major Strasser would insist.
- You're saying this only to make me go.
- I'm saying it because it's true.
Inside of us we both know
you belong with Victor.
You're part of his work,
the thing that keeps him going.
If that plane leaves
and you're not with him, you'll regret it.
Maybe not today, maybe not tomorrow,
but soon, and for the rest of your life.
But what about us?
We'll always have Paris.
We didn't have-- We'd lost it
until you came to Casablanca.
We got it back last night.
- When I said I would never leave you.
- And you never will.
But I've got a job to do too.
Where I'm going, you can't follow.
What I've got to do
you can't be any part of.
Ilsa, I'm no good at being noble.
But it doesn't take much to see
that the problems of three little people...
...don't amount to a hill of beans
in this crazy world.
Someday you'll understand that.
Now, now.
Here's looking at you, kid.
[HORN HONKS]
- Everything is in order.
- All except one thing.
There's something you should know.
I don't ask you to explain anything.
I'm going to anyway.
It may make a difference to you later on.
- You said you knew about Ilsa and me.
- Yes.
You didn't know she was at my place
last night when you were.
She came there for the letters of transit.
Isn't that true, Ilsa?
Yes.
She tried everything to get them.
Nothing worked.
She did her best to convince me
that she was still in love with me.
But that was all over long ago.
For your sake, she pretended it wasn't,
and I let her pretend.
I understand.
- Here it is.
- Thanks.
I appreciate it.
Welcome back to the fight.
This time I know our side will win.
Are you ready, Ilsa?
Yes, I'm ready.
Goodbye, Rick.
God bless you.
You better hurry.
You'll miss that plane.
I was right.
You are a sentimentalist.
Stay where you are.
I don't know what you're talking about.
What you just did for Laszlo.
That fairy tale you invented
to send Ilsa away with him.
I know a little about women, my friend.
She went.
But she knew you were lying.
Anyway, thanks for helping me out.
I suppose you know this isn't
going to be pleasant for either of us.
Especially for you.
- I'll have to arrest you, of course.
- As soon as the plane goes, Louis.
What was the meaning
of that phone call?
Victor Laszlo is on that plane.
Why do you stand here?
Why don't you stop him?
Ask Monsieur Rick.
- Get away from that phone.
- I advise you not to interfere.
I was willing to shoot Captain Renault,
and I'm willing to shoot you.
- Hello!
- Put that phone down.
- Get me the radio tower.
- Put it down!
Major Strasser has been shot.
Round up the usual suspects.
[SPEAKING IN FRENCH]
Well, Rick,
you're not only a sentimentalist...
...but you've become a patriot.
RICK: Maybe, but it seemed
like a good time to start.
I think perhaps you're right.
It might be a good idea for you to
disappear from Casablanca for a while.
There's a Free French garrison
over at Brazzaville.
- I could be induced to arrange a passage.
- My letter of transit?
I could use a trip.
But it doesn't change our bet.
You still owe me 10,000 francs.
That 10,000 francs
should pay our expenses.
RICK: "Our" expenses?
- Mm-hm.
RICK: Louis, I think this is the beginning
of a beautiful friendship.
[English - US - SDH]